Welcome back and today in distributed
microservices we are going to start the
asynchronous communication. So till now
whatever we have done in distributed
microservices where we have more than
one microservices and they're talking to
each other it's mostly happen in a
synchronous manner. But when we are
dealing with microservices the very
important aspect is your eventdriven
architecture the asynchronous
communication. Okay. So in this
topic I will first cover the
introduction of event- driven
architecture. I will not go deep into
okay let's go into this specific
event-driven uh you can say that event
router either Kafka Rabbit MQ or
something. So in this topic my agenda
would be to have a introduction
introduction of EDA. Okay. So yes in
depth explanation of a specific event
router we might go into the next topic
itself. So let's start without wasting
any further time. What is EDA? What is
eventdriven architecture.
So considered it as a system design
style where services do not call each
other directly
instead service emit an event and other
service react to those event. Okay. So
you have one service you have multiple
services you can say that they never
call directly to each other. They just
publish an event. Hey,
now you might say what is an event? When
we are saying hey they emit an event you
might say what is an event then event I
would say in a simple way that something
a fact that something happened in the
past. Okay. So see there are one major
difference between event
order and not order say command.
Event order command and query.
Event means something happened in the
past like order created right? Command
is like you are giving the command. Hey
place an order. Place an order is a
command but order created is an event
which happened. Okay. Query is means
that you are fetching something like hey
fetch me the details of the order which
are placed. So these three are different
things. So when we are saying that
service emit event so event are
immutable.
They cannot be changed once created.
Okay. So it because they are already
created in the past. You can't change
it. What h exactly happened and it's a
past tense like order created. Okay, we
are not saying place order. Place order
means you are giving a command but we
are not giving a command. We just
telling the fact what has happened in
the past. Okay, so past tense is
describe what happened not what to do
and self-contain. So every event has all
the information needed to understand it
better. So once so now
service emits event. So it emits an
event and this event is listened by some
other services.
Okay. And this event contain all the
information
okay and based on that these services
react on top of it. Don't worry about
it. uh but only thing I uh I want you to
understand at this point of time is that
no two services are communicate directly
with each other. They are now
interacting based on events.
One emit an event others consume those
event. Okay. And this event is something
which is immutable like you can't change
it. Order has been created. It's created
now. You can't undo the order creation
part. It's order is created. Now you
listen to that event. Okay, order
created. Now you decide what you want to
do. Okay, but you can't change it.
So in rest distributed microservices,
the same example I would take for an
order creation. Let's say you have a
user service, you have an order service,
you have payment service, inventory
service, notification service. So I have
taken an example of four five services.
Now in the rest distributed
microservices what used to happen is
user place an order. Okay. Now in the
order first it will do it will check the
inventory real time whether inventory is
there or not. Okay. Then it will try to
process the payment. Once the payment is
done it will reserve the inventory and
after the inventory is done it will send
the notification. So these are all
different services and this order
services is now talking with each of the
different services to complete the flow
and after that it returns that order has
been placed successful.
Now in this part if you see here there
are many disadvantages we can easily
see. So problems
the first problem is availability.
All service must be available at the
same time any service down request will
fail. So in this part let's say
to complete this flow
this should be available this should be
available this should be available this
should be available. Let's say even if
inventory goes down this flow cannot be
success. Okay. So the first thing is
availability. Second thing is latency
accumulation.
Your total latency is that sum of all
the service latency like how much time
this place order request takes then this
plus this plus this plus this. You got
it right? So your latency is now
accumulated
t1 + ts2 + t3 + t4 like this
cascading failure. One slow service can
bring down the other service and entire
flow itself.
If for example your order service is
fast, your payment service is fast but
your inventory service is too slow then
there are is a casket failure because
let's say you are sending it 10 requests
but it only able to handle five requests
for five requests it is denying. So
those five failure will cascade to the
payment service and cascade service will
uh you can say that uh the payment
service will cascade it to the order
service. So there is a cascading
failure. Okay.
The tight coupling. The tight coupling
in that in the sense if you see the
order is talking with payment. Order is
talking with inventory. Order is talking
with notification. So order has the
knowledge of all three services. How to
interact? What response I will get and
many other things. So there is a very
tight coupling in this rest distributed
system.
And another thing is scaling issue. We
cannot scale just one service
independent independently. You can't
just scale payment service and your
order service, inventory service,
notification service. Uh let's say it's
not scale that much. So what I mean to
say you scale based on load. So you just
can't scale payment service that okay
earlier it was taking 100 requests per
minute. Now you
increase the scalability and it now it
accept accepting 1,000 requests per
minute. Even though it is accepting
thousand requests but what about
inventory it is not scaled right? So it
will only have the capability to handle
100 requests rest 900 will fail. So
cascading failure impact will come on
this only. So scaling issue is there. So
now here if you see that there are so
this is just you can say the top five I
have listed down
when you have a flow like this when I
say that flow like this means long
running flow. So consider this as a
wrong long running flow order placed
then you check the inventory then you
process the payment then you reserve the
inventory then you send the
notification. So this in the long
running flow means multiple services are
included. Okay. So in that the rest
distributed microservices has various
challenges and these are just top five.
So generally in those scenario
eventdriven architecture is highly used
in the industry. Okay. And again this is
just an example I am showing you
whatever this order service inventory
service. It's not like this is the exact
flow for an order. So consider this just
an example for differentiating what
between rest and the EDA event driven
architecture.
So now in the event-driven architecture
if you have to just design the same
thing into this part. So we still have a
user order service. Now here we have an
event router. So see at this since this
is the first part of this event-driven
architecture
either it could be either Kafka, Rabbit
MQ or any different router you can say
that but here currently you can say that
it's a generic term I have I have used
event router
okay and then you have a let's say
payment service, inventory service,
notification service. Now we have
everything same but apart from that we
have another uh you can say that kind of
uh platform like a event router.
Now what happened the first is user
place an order. Now here if you see that
I am doing a realtime processing still
check the realtime inventory. Yes, if
inventory is present save order status
equals to pending
and it will publish an event to this
event router that order created. So one
event is published. So this is an event
event publish order created and it send
the response to the user order is
accepted. Okay. So your first part is
completed. So now here if you see user
got the response very early
and till now what we have done is we
have just stored the order in the
pending state and we have just publish
an event that order created event uh to
this event router. Okay. And the
response has been gone to the user that
order accepted. Now the second lag which
is a sync now it's doesn't have to be in
real time. Okay. So now as sync and
parallel processing here in this box.
So now the event has been published
right to this event router what order
created. So what it will do this event
router it will push the order created
event to all those who are interested.
Okay. So now let's say that payment
service is interested in this event and
inventory service is also interested in
this event order created event. Okay. So
now here if you see that it just push
the event it don't tell anything what
you have to do it just tell that hey
order is created now whatever you have
to do do it
now payment service what it will do is
it will try to process the payment
inventory service try to reserve the
inventory and once done they will also
publish their event hey my payment
success is done okay and reserve
inventory. Hey, I am able to reserve the
inventory properly. It just publish an
event. So these are also an event.
Now
event router in the third line
whoever is interested into payment
success event it will push the event to
that. Now let's say notification service
is interested in payment success event.
So it just push the event. So now here
if you see what event router is doing is
services
publish an event and what event router
is doing is pass the event to the other
services which are interested. So it act
as a mediator or a broker.
Okay.
So now let's say in this one uh when
payment service publish an event that
hey payment has been success this broker
this event router what it does is it
just pass this event to whichever other
service are interested in. So
notification service is interested in
this event and it now got the payment
success event. So it send the mail okay
and it also send this payment success
event to order service and it will
update its status to completed.
This is just an example to show that in
case of event-driven architecture
different microservices are talking with
each other based on events.
Okay. So the same flow we are dividing
or you can say that modifying into this
EDA and this is one perfect use case
where EDA can be used.
Okay.
So what are the advantages of
eventdriven architecture from the above
flow we can see
very simple like whatever the
disadvantages of synchronous chain we
have seen generally are the advantages
of event-driven architecture. One thing
is loose coupling no direct dependency
on one another.
Scalability service can scale
independently like now you can scale
payment service as much as you want. Uh
it can process payment like depending
upon the event it can accept so many
events. It can process the events. So
now it can scale independently. Okay.
Better resilience temporary issue do not
break the whole system. Now let's say
that reserve inventory is failing but
the whole system is not down.
order is still getting accepted. Okay,
maybe for temporary purpose it is
failing but once it is get up all the
pending events it can go and start
working on it. So your system is not
completely failed. Okay,
replay we can reprocess the old event
that capability is there. Improvement in
latency. Yes, for sure. Uh because you
are doing ing processing, parallel
processing and even the response time to
the user is
improved a lot. Now user don't have to
wait till this whole let's say 5 second.
Now user has to wait only let's say 1
second. Here it got the response. But
now because of using parallel processing
and all uh everything will get complete
sooner.
Okay. So latency get improved.
So from the above understanding
can we take out the key components? The
key component is we have a producer
the service which publish an event. The
service which publish an event.
Then we have a broker the router. So it
accept the event and what it will do is
it will pass the event to consumer. So
what is consumer service
which
act on the events you can say that which
act on the events or which consume the
events. Okay. So producer publish an
event and event broker or router pass
the event to a specific
services which are interested in it.
So these these are the major components
of event-driven architecture very high
level.
Now the next thing uh introductory part
I would just say that how do events move
through this. Okay. So how the events
move through event-driven architecture.
Now let's say events are published. Now
from here how it got passed to this.
Okay. So one is push model. In the push
model what happen is producer publish an
event to the broker and the broker push
the message immediately to the consumer
which are interested in these events.
Now consumer must handle whatever rate
broker send and sometime it is possible
that consumer can get overwhelmed with
it. Okay. Another is pull model. In the
pull model producer publishes an event
to a broker. Now broker store the
messages.
Consumer can ask from the broker that
hey give me this many messages. Broker
will send that. consumer process at its
own pace and then ask more messages
again and continue the process. So this
is known as pull model.
So there are many uh you can say that
broker which works on pull model, push
model or both. We will see that. But
this is just a very uh high level
understanding that we can have here push
and pull model also.
So that when we so this is consider that
that we are not going in depth how push
model works that is depending upon like
which framework we are using let's say
if you go with Kafka then how the
pushpull works in Kafka then we have to
go independently into that framework
flow okay if you're going with rabbit mq
how push pull model we have to enable
how it works we have to go into that but
here today the intention is that We know
the term that's all. Okay.
Then there is something called EDM
model. So there are two types of EDM
model. One is pubsub and another is
streaming. So whenever somebody say that
pub uh pops up Google pops up you you
might have heard of right uh publisher
subscriber model generally
events are published to active consumers
and then forgotten
if new consumer joined let's say
tomorrow it won't get yesterday messages
because messages are not stored
and whatever Whatever the active
consumers are there only they will get
the events. Okay. So they the pops sub
model do not have capability to replay
the events or to store the events or
maintain the history. You can say that
like rabbit MQ exchange.
Then another model is streaming model.
Events are appended in logs forever or
retain based. So you can decide whether
you want to retain for 7 days, 3 days, 4
days or you don't want to delete at all.
So events are stored in logs and we can
replay
right. So that
is possible with the streaming. So now
let's say that if new consumer joined
say tomorrow, new consumer joined
tomorrow and it can read it can decide
that it can read from the latest offset
or read from the day one. This is
possible because we are retaining the
data like from the day you have written
you can start from that day also.
Okay. Example is our Kafka. So a Kafka
is a streaming model there logs are
stored. Rabbit MQ is your popsup where
uh you can say that events are not
restored.
[snorts]
But what are the challenges of
event-driven architecture? Currently
everything looks good, right? We have so
many advantages that there are so many
challenges and these are critical
like you can say that whenever you are
working in the highle design part of u
any any uh question where you have to
use eventdriven architecture mostly the
questions or challenges comes into this
part. The first challenge is its
eventual consistence. Eventual
consistency means let's say
it is processing something in a sing
manner. Now when you hit it let's say
get call you might get a stale data a
stale or old data but eventually when
you hit another after some time you
might get latest updated data. So it's
an eventual consistence. You might get a
stale data if you try quickly but
eventually if you try after some time
you might get latest up-to-date data
duplicate events. See the event routers
guarantee at least once delivery. So it
can deliver events more than once. So
duplicates are normal. So we have to
handle it properly.
Ordering problems. Now let's say that
your publisher has published
two events but the consumer got first
event two and then event one. This is
very very important problem. Okay. So
this need to be handled very well.
Okay. So we'll see that we will share
real world problems how we will pick one
topic and we'll try to build out all
these things. Okay. But today we just
highlighting the challenges and each
challenge we have to solve. Okay. So
when we will go with let's say Kafka
and when we will build Kafka then after
that we have to go one by one all the
challenges there would be more. So here
I have just listed around six seven but
there are so many so we have to take one
challenges and see how it has to be
industry standard to solve those
challenges. But I wanted to just mention
here that there are so many challenges.
It's not like EDA is perfect. Another is
schema evolution. If you break the
schema, all consumer will crash. Right?
Because I told you event has a specific
schema which has all the information and
consumers consume this events. So if you
change something in this schema,
you remove something or you updated
something. So consumers might need to be
updated also otherwise they will crash.
So you need to maintain the versioning
properly
debugging complexity. Distributed
tracing across a syncing hops are little
difficult because now everything is
happening inc manner. So see this is
happening in a singing manner. This is
happening in parallel. So when parallel
and comes into the picture debugging is
not that easy. Okay. So yes, debugging
got a little bit complex or here poison
message generally one bad message can
block the event router itself. So
I don't I won't go into this deep what
is poison message here now because it
will complicate the things and to
understand the poison message like I
need to tell the framework first like
whichever we are discussing but
understand that there are
because events are published to this
event router let's say if one event is
bad okay and nobody is able to consume
it and what if that event is is still
kept into the event router. Okay, so
very high level you can say that there
are possibilities that one bad message
also can block the event router too that
generally known as poison message. So
that challenge is also present.
Then again another challenge we have is
operational overhead. You have to
monitor the consumer lag. Okay. Hey, you
are publishing an event five per minute
but consumer is able to consume or
process only one per minute. So how much
delay [snorts] is lagging? Monitor the
que is Q is able to maintain the
events which are getting published or
not. Okay. What is the throughput
partitions and all? So you need to
maintain everything size and all. So
there is an operational overhead also.
So it is not like you just use EDA and
everything works out of the box. It is
little
you can say that uh proper understanding
proper knowledge is required otherwise
these challenges are so critical that
instead of getting advantage we might uh
get into more trouble. Okay, our DB
could get easily corrupted very easily.
Okay, this order problem itself if not
handled properly it could easily corrupt
the DB itself.
Now what are the use cases of
event-driven architecture? Like sometime
what happen is we need to have a mindset
like okay when I should go for rest when
I should go for event- driven
architecture. So there are see many
scenarios but high level I will give you
four. One is that one event and there
are multiple consumers for that event.
Then it's a very clear indication that
we have to use event-driven
architecture. Let's say for example
order is placed then inventory has to do
something payment has to do something
email notification service has to do
something the analytics team has to do
something. So you can't order can't talk
with all of them. Okay. So it can
publish an event and you can do whatever
you want to do. Okay. So it's a very
good use case for the event-driven
architecture and that's why I have used
that for an example
longunning business workflow. That's the
same thing that here if you see when
transaction is started and when your
transaction got end you can say that.
Okay. So order, payment, shipment,
delivery like everything
should be up successful and then only
your
order placement is done. So it's a very
long running business flow. Okay. And
it's a failure prone. Okay. It can be
you can say that something can be failed
in the midway.
Okay. And this flow takes a lot of time.
So if the flow is not in the critical
path then we can say that it can be
broken into multi-step which is a
failureprone.
Okay. So you can always think critical
part
non-critical
part. So critical part should be always
real time. Okay. Like here I am doing
that.
This is my critical part.
Check the real time inventory. I don't
want to do it in a singing. When I get
the place order request, I check real
time stored into the DB status request
to pending publish an event. This is all
my critical. Okay, that's why I'm doing
in a real time not in a sing.
So once this is done then my
non-critical part starts which I can go
for eventdriven architecture that okay
even if it takes some time even let's
say it can take 2 seconds more or let's
say 4 seconds more it's not like
something is very urgently waiting so
consider that as a non-critical part
okay so we can think of that it's a good
use case for EDA
Another is eventual consistency is
acceptable. If you are have a use case
where eventual consistency is okay, then
it's a very good hint that EDA might be
used.
realtime analytics like data is
continuously coming and you have to work
on that data then definitely it's an EDA
use case like multiple events are
continuously coming coming and you have
a consumer which continuously consuming
those events and doing some realtime
analytics okay data need to be
continuously processed then is also a
use case of EDA so this is very high
level four use cases of EDA but we can
have more and this is Just one
introductory video of what is EDA before
we jump into a specific event router and
most probably I will pick Kafka for it.
Okay. Okay guys, see you soon. Bye.